# Benjamin B. Daniels

benjamin.daniels@georgetown.edu

benjaminbdaniels.com github.com/bbdaniels +1 (203) 687-9943

## **PROFILE**

# International public health researcher with 10 years of experience and a passion for teaching

Academic researcher specializing in the quality of primary health care and public health Statistical programming expert, best practice designer, and tool developer for reproducible research Teacher, trainer, and mentor, designing and leading professional development and immersive courses Fieldwork planner and manager in collaboration with local clients and partners Supervisor and manager of graduate students, research assistants, consultants, and contractors

#### **EDUCATION**

MSc Economics and Philosophy, London School of Economics and Social Science BA Economics, Pomona College

London, UK, 2013 Claremont, CA, 2011

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# **Georgetown University**

2019 - Present

Fellow, Georgetown University Initiative on Innovation, Development and Evaluation (gui<sup>2</sup>de)

- Co-authored peer-reviewed studies focusing on primary health care quality and public health
- · Managed grant proposals and IRB registrations, and supported PhD students in dissertation work
- Co-developed "Research Fieldwork & Analysis" all-levels course (launching Fall 2022)
- · Won \$20k grant for "Advancing Precision Medicine with E-Health Records & Machine Learning"
- · Developed and executed data-sharing agreement with World Bank and Harvard for Estonian health records
- Co-won \$150k World Bank SIEF grant and \$100k DEC grant for impact evaluation using Estonian data.

# The World Bank — Development Economics Vice Presidency (DEC) Washington, DC, and international

**2011 – Present** 

Data Coordinator, Development Impact Evaluations Department (DIME Analytics)

2017 - Present

- · Co-authored published training manual Development Research in Practice: The DIME Analytics Data Handbook
- · Planned and delivered "Development Research in Practice" course to over 2,000 global participants
- · Created Research Assistant Onboarding Sequence and Continuing Education training seminars
- · Designed and led Advanced Stata track for "Manage Successful Impact Evaluations" flagship training
- · Developed and implemented department-wide standards practices for high-quality and reproducible research
- · Envisioned and expanded the DIME Wiki, Research Standards, Reproducibility Checks, and training series
- · Contributed to World Bank and DIME GitHub, including publication and licensing standards for code and data
- · Contributed to Stata code packages iefieldkit and ietoolkit for standard data collection and analysis
- · Supported design and data on all projects, including sampling, randomization, and SurveyCTO Enterprise
- Organized and executed "Reproducibility, Transparency, and Credibility: A Research Symposium"
- · Supported recruitment including developing and executing batch hiring, interviews, and technical evaluation

Researcher, Quality of Tuberculosis Care in Urban India (QuTUB)

2011 - 2019

- · Managed data collection and analysis for \$1.3M study on tuberculosis (TB) care in urban India
- · Supported design and implementation of RCT evaluation of TB care programs in Mumbai and Patna
- · Handled on-site coordination and data sharing with local implementing NGOs
- · Managed data collection process over 10 survey rounds totaling 10,000 standardized patient (SP) interactions
- · Led analysis of data resulting in various peer-reviewed publications
- · Analyzed NGO programmatic data on 200,000 real patients to assess patterns of provider behavior change

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- **Development Research in Practice: The DIME Analytics Data Handbook.** Washington, DC: The World Bank. https://openknowledge.worldbank.org/handle/10986/35594. With K Bjärkefur, LC de Andrade, and M Jones.
- "Prescribing practices for presumptive TB among private general practitioners in South Africa: A cross-sectional, standardised patient study." *BMJ Global Health* 7.1 (2022): e007456. With A Salomon, et al.
- "Simulated patients and their reality: An inquiry into theory and method." *Social Science & Medicine* (2021): 114571. With V Das, et al.
- "Human capital accumulation and disasters: Evidence from the Pakistan earthquake of 2005." *Journal of Human Resources* (2021): 0520-10887R1. With T Andrabi and J Das.
- "Quality of care for tuberculosis and HIV in the private health sector: A cross-sectional, standardised patient study in South Africa." *BMJ Global Health* 6.5 (2021): e005250. With J Boffa, et al.
- "iefieldkit: Stata commands for primary data collection and cleaning." *The Stata Journal* 20, no. 4 (2020): 892-915. With K Bjärkefur and LC de Andrade.
- "Primary care providers are, fundamentally, risk managers And this is a challenge for health policy." *The Lancet Regional Health–Western Pacific* 3 (2020).
- "Two Indias: The structure of primary health care markets in rural Indian villages with implications for policy." *Social Science & Medicine* (2020): https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.112799. With J Das, et al.
- "Antibiotic overuse in the primary health care setting: A secondary data analysis of standardised patient studies from India, China and Kenya." *BMJ Global Health*, 5(9), p.e003393. (2020) With G Sulis, et al.
- "Antibiotic prescription practices in primary care in low- and middle-income countries: A systematic review and metaanalysis." *PLOS Medicine* (2020) 17(6): e1003139. With G Sulis, et al.
- "Covid-19 Diaries: Early Impressions from an Online Questionnaire." In "Covid-19 and Student Focused Concerns: Threats and Possibilities," *American Ethnologist* (2020). With J Das, et al.
- "Use of standardised patients for healthcare quality research in low-and middle-income countries." *BMJ Global Health* 4.5 (2019): e001669. With A Kwan, et al.
- "How to do (or not to do) ... using the standardized patient method to measure clinical quality of care in LMIC health facilities." *Health Policy and Planning* (2019) With J King, et al.
- "Lessons on the quality of tuberculosis diagnosis from standardized patients in China, India, Kenya, and South Africa." *J. Clinical Tuberculosis and Other Mycobacterial Diseases* (2019) Jun 7:100109. With A Kwan, et al. (first author)
- "Use of standardised patients to assess gender differences in quality of tuberculosis care in urban India: A two-city, cross-sectional study" *Lancet Global Health* (2019) 7:e633-e643. With A Kwan, et al. (joint first author)
- "Variations in the quality of tuberculosis care in urban India: A cross-sectional, standardized patient study in two cities." *PLoS Medicine* (2018) 15.9:e1002653. With A Kwan, et al. (joint first author)
- "Use of standardised patients to assess quality of healthcare in Nairobi, Kenya: A pilot, cross-sectional study with international comparisons." *BMJ Global Health* (2017) 2:e000333. With A Dolinger, et al. (first author)
- "Social equity issues in the distribution of feed-in tariff policy benefits: A cross sectional analysis from England and Wales using spatial census and policy data." *Energy Policy* (2017) 106:255-65. With D Grover.
- "Use of standardised patients to assess antibiotic dispensing for tuberculosis by pharmacies in urban India: A cross-sectional study." *Lancet Infectious Diseases* (2016) 15:30215-8. With S Satyanarayana, et al.
- "Examining the quality of medicines at Kenyan healthcare facilities: A validation of an alternate post-market surveillance model that uses standardized patients." *Drugs Real World Outcomes* (2016) 1-11. With F Wafula, et al.
- "Quality and Equity in Basic Health Care Services in Vietnam: Findings from the 2015 Vietnam District and Commune Health Facility Survey." World Bank Report No. AUS13083. (2016) With G Demombynes, et al.
- "Use of standardised patients to assess quality of tuberculosis care: A pilot, cross-sectional study." *Lancet Infectious Diseases* (2015) 15:1305-13. With J Das, et al.

## **MISCELLANEOUS**